this is software engineering radio a
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the background
okay welcome listeners to another
episode on softening radio today we have
came back on the mic and talked with him
about the history of j-unit and the
future of unit testing so a welcome Kent
thank you very much it's great to be
here great to have you on the show
would you introduce yourself to our
listeners tell us a little bit about
your history in your background
sure well I'm a third generation geek my
grandfather was a radio geek my dad was
an electrical engineering geek turned
programmer geek and now now I am and now
my my oldest daughter and carries on the
family tradition so I grew up in an
environment with lots of Technology
around started programming when I was
about 12 or 13 maybe maybe 11 on a
programmable calculator my dad brought
home and hmm let's see I don't know what
kind of highlights the listeners will
find interesting
I'll just I've done a number of things
software patterns were something that I
worked on or early on extreme
programming test-driven development the
xunit architecture which was first
implemented in small talk and then
translated into java by Erich gamma and
myself responsive design hmm well what
else what else are you interested in you
wrote a lot of books they're great yes I
think I've written eight books so far oh
wow I think they're pretty pretty famous
in the in the community right yeah bye
bye geek standards yes okay great and I
think I read on Twitter that you you're
your great fan of the radio episodes it
is that correct
yes so I live on on eight hectares of a
mixture of meadows and forests outside
of a little village which it's outside
of
a slightly larger town in the middle of
nowhere in Southern Oregon so I have a
lot of farm chores to do and I listen to
lots of podcasts including having
listened to I think all of the episodes
of software engineering radio it's great
when you're shoveling manure to be able
to tune into something to feed your
brain while you're while you're taking
care of that or feeding the animals or
whatever yeah cool I think it's a great
honor to have you as a as a as a
listener for all the episodes it's great
cool um so can you tell us a little bit
about the history of j-unit how things
began sure so I my first commercial work
was in small talk and small talk had a
history of testing but not automated
testing so you'd make a few changes to
your programs and then you'd run a
little bit and then you'd make some more
changes and it was set up for that kind
of very incremental cycle but there
there weren't automated tests I did a
series of experiments so I tried four or
five different techniques for writing
automated tests and then and then one
day I was asked to give advice to a
development project early on in my
consulting career and I knew I was going
to tell them to write automated tests
but I didn't have a way for them to
write automated tests so kind of in a
panic I said let me take this structure
that we use for testing and small talk
this is a workspace structure where you
have some variables that would get
initialized and then you'd have
expressions and I said well what if I
just turned that naively into an object
model so the workspace is a class the
variables that you use become instance
variables the the little snippets of
code that you use to test become methods
so it was just really kind of the naive
mapping and then rather than doing the
manual testing where we'd say you'll
print this value out and then you'd make
sure that yes it printed out ABC I said
well let's have the computer do that so
that's where that's where the assertions
from so that was the origins of the of
the architecture and that's got to be in
1980 mmm you know I can't remember he's
yeah I don't have a date an exact date
for you but that's now it's got to be in
the 90s 92 so that's when the first unit
testing framework that I did that was at
all successful came from fast forward a
few years I was living in Zurich and
Eric gamma and I would get together and
then program from time to time and Java
was fairly new at that time and I wanted
to learn it so we were on the plane
going to upsala and he'd heard me
talking about this this testing
architecture and I'd heard him talking
about how cool Java less and so we just
sat there and and built the first
version of j-unit test first from the
very first which is an interesting
bootstrap problem right how do you test
the testing framework so that if it
breaks you know that it breaks so we you
know we like those kind of intellectual
challenges so by the time we were done
with that plane ride we had the first
version of Jane unit we gave it to
Martin Fowler I mean it but it was so
small right J unit is so small how could
this possibly be valuable so we gave it
to Martin Fowler there in Atlanta he
tried it out immediately and said this
is cool so we gave it out to several
more people got really good feedback and
that's pretty much how the whole thing
started Wow
and it's a pretty successful story right
today j-unit is the lead efecto standard
for for doing automated unit testing in
java right correct
so what happens since then it's a long
time ago what happened to J unit in the
meantime yeah so that was in in 97 that
we wrote the first version and so it's
gone through
now on version 4 is gone through one big
architectural change which was the
switch from sub classing a framework
sort of metaphor where you subclass
something and overrode certain methods
to a DSL metaphor which you implement in
Java with annotations so I had seen in
unit very early on when it was just a
few files on on James Newkirk's machine
and seeing the annotations I thought
this is a cool idea and then I realized
well a lot of the way that for instance
methods used to have to begin with the
letters T est well it's a kind of
metadata because we would go and
interpret that yeah you know J unit is a
language it has semantics they're
different from Java semantics for an ant
for example inheritance runs differently
than that than it does in Java but so we
were we were using the language - we
created this language in Java that
wasn't really Java and interpreting it
but with annotations now all of a sudden
the compiler can give you help again
because if somebody named their test TSE
T it just wouldn't run and there'd be no
way to tell but with the annotation you
know whether it's spelled correctly
there are a lot of other language
implementations of the jejune framework
a lot of translations to other languages
what do you think of this is this
movement well I think I can interpret it
on a couple of levels one level is this
is a successful design I mean it means
that there is something common to tests
that is that you want to run these
isolated chunks you want to be able to
compose them together and not have them
interfere with each other and you want
to do that all in the source language I
mean there's huge advantages to not
having your testing language be your
source language but there's also huge
advantages to keeping the the source
language on the test testing language it
they have it in the same in the same
language as it is with the with J unit
so kind of there's this attractor in the
space of design tools and you know it
draws a lot of functionality into that
same basic shape today was implementing
the current versions you're still
working an IDE right yes yes so every
week David SAFF who's at Google now and
I get together and work on it for for a
few hours know every week yeah pretty
much
Wow cool so you're already planning the
next version yes we're already working
on it we don't have a big new theme I
would say the the last version came out
with a really cool feature which is kind
of working its way through the community
that's one of the things the advantages
of having a project that lasts for 13
years is you learn a little bit the
value of patience so you know just if
you come up with a new feature and you
think it's fantastic five years later if
people are using it then yeah that was a
really cool feature but you can't you
can't tell after you know if it's only
been three years and people still aren't
using it then you still don't know
whether it was really cool or not so and
that was what we call rules which are
kind of hmm let's see what's a simple
way to explain it so when your test runs
this chain of objects is created that
you know one object will run the before
methods and another object will will
catch timeouts and another object will
report errors well you can insert using
rules you can insert objects into this
chain so it's kind of a meta object for
testing and so it was a big deal people
are using it for all
cool stuff rather than having to use
inheritance to capture the commonality
of of tests now you can use composition
which is a whole lot more flexible so if
people are looking for the the cool
stuff in j-unit that would be that would
be something to have a look at so I
think it's a key feature to reuse stuff
in your unit testing code I don't know
if it's a key feature because you know
when we went 13 years without it so but
I think it is very useful
certainly for capturing I mean I always
strive for a kind of declarative
expression in my tests you should be
able to just kind of read a test and it
tells a story and rules are a way of
setting the stage for a test in a way
that's obvious you can read right there
but you know at the same time can be
quite simple you know so you can have a
rule that creates a temporary folder and
then all of the stuff that you do in
your test that does file manipulation
when the test finishes the folders
automatically deleted so so in reading
the test you can just say oh look
there's a temporary folder I'm sure
there's some file manipulation going on
in here so rules give in an imperative
language this still gives it this very
declarative feel which I think is is
valuable for tests ok so it's not only
these kind of reusing stuff but also to
make it more more expressive right yes
cuz every test should tell a story right
it should have a you know beginning a
middle and end it should have a kind of
a flow and arc and it should have a
moral right what's the point what's the
point of this test you should be able to
read that out of the test so rules give
another way of setting the context for
test that's a little richer than
anything that happened before and it's
introduced in version 4 point the eight
I think four point eight yeah which is
what you can find on github that's where
we where we host now after a long and
successful run on source
okay great so you also mentioned these
that he worked on on or you maybe you
coined the term test-driven development
so can give you a very brief
introduction what test-driven
development is it's this crazy idea that
you the best ideas are the crazy ones
right if you have a crazy idea and it
works it's really valuable if you have a
if you have a fantastic idea
and it works who cares right because
somebody else will have thought it but
if you have a crazy idea and it works
then you really have something so it's
it's this crazy idea that you when you
want to code the first thing you do is
you write a test that fails that will
only succeed when the code that you're
imagining is actually in place so it
turns the workflow of of programming
backwards what do you think is the most
important point when you do test-driven
development is that that you think about
the design first or the drive drive the
implementation from the viewpoint of a
user of the class for example because
you write the test first or is it
something else here's what happened to
my head after I'd been doing TDD for a
couple of years and that is I would
imagine some functionality and my next
thought was how am I going to test that
always before I would imagine some
functionality and then I would think ah
you know I could subclass this and
extract that as an object and replace it
and I bump a bump a bump it's all about
implementation and now when I think
about functionality my next thought is
how am I going to test that what it does
for my thinking is that trying to
imagine the implementation and how I
will know that it's correct at the same
time because I make mistakes is is a big
job sometimes it's too big for me to
hold in my head if I can divide that
into two parts and handle the how am I
going to test this part first then I
have a smaller less stressful easier to
focus on
to deal with namely how am I going to
test this oh well if you can't write a
test for you got no business programming
it which is true for most programs now
when I'm being very exploratory I don't
worry about this stuff you know if I
just want to say can I get a program
that does X at all then I'll just sling
code and check it manually then once I
discover yes this is possible then it's
a good time to to switch gears and say
okay now you know let me go back and let
me in this a little at a time and figure
out how I'm going to test this for many
people where I talk with him they still
think that doing the test before the
actual code is really a crazy idea
and there isn't maybe means something
they're afraid of doing this kind of
stuff what is your observation of the
adoption of of test-driven development
in practice and industry in the wild
well I'm really curious like what could
go wrong your heads not going to explode
like what so do you do TDD yeah so what
do you say when somebody says oh this
isn't gonna work typically I say it
helps me just go forward in small steps
and and keeps me going at a sustainable
pace in small steps and it just helps me
thinking about what I need to do and
then how can I possibly be implemented
stuff yeah that's this that's a sense
that I I have that's my experience of it
as well now it is I think some of the
barriers are probably social because
when I went to computer science school
you know back when we had to dig our own
sand for our own transistors the good
the a students got to be programmers and
the B students had to be testers so part
of what I had to overcome was just kind
of this the social status oh I'm a
programmer you know I don't have to
write tests and and and like I had to
overcome that you know that I was
somehow lowering myself to write tests
which isn't true I mean that makes
no sense but that this is a human brain
we're talking about so so I you know I
don't know if that's part of what the
people you're talking to are
encountering but that was certainly
certainly a barrier for me to think yeah
I should spend 30 40 percent of my time
recognizably writing tests now when I'm
writing tests I'm not just writing tests
I'm making API decisions I'm making
analysis decisions and the test just
happened to be the notation that I use
to record those decisions but at the end
I still do have a bunch of tests that
actually run do you think you you've
convinced most of the people you talk to
I don't know cuz I'm not I don't try to
convince people anymore I think I spent
probably 10 years really trying to
convince people TDD pair program and you
should do this you should do that and I
don't do that anymore
I'm always working to improve my own
practice I am eager to share what I
learn and I try and listen and
understand what other people have
learned in their experience as well so I
don't like I don't really keep score by
how many people do TDD if the practice
of software development is improving
overall then I think that's a great
thing and if I have some small influence
on that then I think that's a great
thing too well so you asked a question
about do people like how widespread is
is TDD I think it's still a very small
percentage of people that are like won't
write a line of code unless they have a
test that's failing you know under for
production coding but I think there are
a very large number of people that have
been exposed to tests and the potential
value of tests but I still go places and
people say oh yeah we did a bunch of
tests but then the test stopped working
so we threw them out which just seems
bizarre
to me I mean like Aristotle would be
shocked right the logic just doesn't add
up this test said if the test is running
my programs running it if the Testament
is not running then my program is not
running and the test stops running and
your next act is to delete the test or
just stop running it or ignore the test
report that you get like wow that means
your programs not running but somehow I
mean there's a lot of other pressures on
people other than get your program
running I guess that's the that's the
conclusion that I can draw from that but
it's kind of its kind of it's too bad I
think there's there's potential value
there people could produce more value as
programmers if they trusted the tests
and paid more attention to them but I
you know there's a lot of other things
going on in software development than
coding there are other let's say maybe
test philosophies for example some
people called behavior driven
development instead of doing test-driven
development what do you think about that
well so the the big picture I think is
very positive
programmers actively taking
responsibility for the quality of their
work I think that's that's a good thing
and whatever you call it kind of that's
a second-order effect something I didn't
communicate very effectively and my
first discussions of TDD is the
importance of working of testing at
various scales so TDD is not a unit
testing philosophy I write tests at
whatever scale I need them to be to help
me make my next step of progress so
sometimes they're very you know they're
what somebody else would call a
functional test so for example 40% of
the tests of j-unit work through the
public API 60% of them are working on
lower-level objects the the public API
is
is quite good for testing probably
because we've written so many tests so I
don't know if those proportions are our
I don't want to claim those proportions
or anything more than one data point
like should you have 40 60 should you
have ten ninety or ninety ten I I really
don't know but just this idea of moving
part of the skill of TDD is learning to
move between scales right so I write a
test that my customer says Oh blah blah
you know this scenario should result in
a five so you write a test that says
this scenario should result in a five
and then you're down in the deep in the
intestines of your program and you're
thinking oh I see you well this object
when given a five and a seven should
return the five well that's a good place
to write a test because that's another
piece of the story that needs to be told
but you know is that acceptance
test-driven development or is that BDD
I'd you know I mean I think that
erecting rigid walls between the styles
is actually a mistake like this the
scales as a programmer I want to
understand all those scales tests help
me understand so I write tests at all
those scales does that it's your
question yeah I think so
and it also leads me to another one
about scaling unit testing because I I
saw projects having thousands and
thousands of unit testing and they had
problems let's say dealing with all
those huge amounts of unit testing what
do you think about this this kind of
does unit testing really scale let's say
on the small level not the acceptance
testing level but on the small level you
have thousands of classes and then huge
amounts of unit testing code maybe two
or three times as much unit testing code
as your actual real production code what
is your experience with that well I
would say that's two to three X a
testing code to production code the
production code have to be pretty
complicated but that's well within the
realm of normal the the guy I learned
the most about testing from was a
compiler writer and and he had five
lines of tests for every line of
compiler that he wrote and he was the
most productive guy that I'd ever seen
so that was a real inspiration to me but
he's working on a compiler which is you
know extremely complicated inside so if
it was 1 to 1 or 5 to 1 it wouldn't it
that wouldn't bother me but you still
think that you need some kind of let's
say test-driven development oi oi
testing automated tests on different
levels of scale right these kind of very
small tests for for very small units I'm
some API stuff some acceptance level
stuff
yeah SAFF claims that David's half the
other current commits Iran Jannah he
claims that tests tend to migrate either
to the lowest level of objects or the
highest and he was talking about tests
for Eclipse applications and so I you
know I can I can believe that I don't
know if that I've really noticed that in
my experience I think I think that I
have some tests and kind of them and a
lovable that that I'm happy to have and
that don't cost me too much
um you already mentioned that you for
example if you would like to figure out
if that's if it's possible to implement
X you don't write a test for it if you
just would like to figure out is it
possible to implement this um are there
other situations where you think you do
not test-driven development but the
other way around so I remember it tweet
on Twitter saying you know something
like good developers know when to test
and when not test can you explain us a
little bit well so the with test you've
got costs and benefits and some of the
benefits or short term and some of the
benefits are long-term some of the costs
are short-term some are long
and different situations have different
profiles of short and long-term so for
example I threw together a site called
poker workout calm because I was
learning to play poker and I was having
trouble doing the pattern matching just
figuring out I have seven cards what
kind of hand do I have do I have a pair
do I have two pairs so first I just
wanted to know if I had a program like
this would it be fun to use and would I
you know would my recognition skills
improve so I just banged it together a
first version in small talk then I
translated it into JavaScript and I
didn't have tests but I discovered yes
this is fun to play so then I wanted to
expand it to you know more situations
and I had to make the domain model
richer and to cover more of poker and
when I did that then I started writing
tests and when I started writing tests I
discovered you know that the the design
was the chunks were too big so I had to
pull pieces out and then I could write
tests more easily for them but there's
this there's this transition period at
first right I could easily have said is
this fun useful at all and the answer
could be no so all the long-term
benefits of having carefully written
tests for that are gone because the you
know the half-life of the program is so
short once I say yes this is good and
yes I want to maintain it and yes I'm
going to live with this code for a while
then the long-term benefits kick in they
become you know more probable that I'll
be able to reap benefits long term so
then I need to kind of switch gears but
well overall that's what I'm thinking
about what are the costs and benefits
short term and long term so when I
started JUnit max which is an eclipse
plug-in writing tests for Eclipse
plug-in CERN is notorious
difficult you know and I I wrote a book
about it with Eric and I still find it a
real challenge sometimes as the API is
is extremely powerful and flexible but
it's not set up for isolated testing
very well so when I when I started Jana
max I didn't have automated tests not
because I knew I was gonna live with
this code for awhile because I just knew
that max was a great idea and I wanted
it for myself and I'd maintain it for
myself if no one else but the cost of
writing those tests was gonna be
extremely high especially the first few
of them that I wrote so for the first
same month that I was developing max I
didn't have any automated tests I did
all my testing manually at some point
the complexity of the code got to where
I was started worrying about if I change
this am I gonna break something else and
that's when I had to as we say in
English bite the bullet you know do
something difficulty in spite of its
difficulty and just start writing tests
now now I have nine I was gonna say lots
I have sufficient tests automated tests
for max but in that exploratory phase
because the short-term costs were so
high even though I knew I was going to
reap the long-term benefits I still
didn't write automated tests for that
and again I had to get become aware of
this balance I'm waving my arms around
here which doesn't really help you I
understand I to become we're aware of
where this balance shifted to where the
costs and benefits short term and long
term now said ah yes duh you know the
previous feature I did without an
automated test in this feature I'm gonna
do with an automated test even if I have
to pay a substantial price to write that
test and and I was happy with how that
worked out so I think that's what I'm
thinking
yes it's very interesting because I also
know people that are much more dogmatic
about unit testing and test-driven
development and they say before you
implement is in line of whatever
is to test-driven development because it
helps you thinking about the piece of
code designing the piece of kill
whatever and they are very much more
dogmatic than than you are it's
interesting to see different opinions
about this well I think it's worth being
dogmatic as as a learning tool right
what if I just said I'm always gonna
write tests for everything and then you
discover oh I'm glad I did this
here I'm sorry that I did it so I won't
do it in you know what's the commonality
in the experiences where I wished that I
hadn't written tests
what's the commonality and the
experiences where I'm glad I wrote the
tests then let me and I'll use that to
inform my behavior going forward some
people that actually writing in their
blocks that are discussing it that
people are today writing too many unit
tests yeah but what is your experience
or your opinion well let's let that be a
big problem before we try and fix it
okay I you know this is it's kind of
it's kind of one of these three bears
things where you know there's certainly
too little and there's maybe too much
and there's someplace in the middle
that's just right do you have do you
have Goldilocks and the three bears in
Germany do you know this story I'm not
sure little girl goes into the Bears
house and she eats the Papa's porridge
and it's too hot and she eats the
mamma's porridge and it's too cold and
then she eats the baby's baby bears
porridge and it's just right okay so
when I say Goldilocks I mean you know
you yes you could have too much you
could have too little in some place in
the middle is right but I don't think
people really know what what too much
really is I would want to examine both
the tests and the activities of a team
that felt like they had too many unit
tests to understand more about that I've
never achieved it and I've tried okay
what do you think what what makes it a
good test a good unit test and what what
makes a bad test a better unit test I'm
pretty sure you've seen a lot of good
and a lot of bad tests sure why
think every test has got to tell a story
that is somebody coming along later and
reading it should be able to understand
something important about the program so
my first filter is is kind of a human
communication filter test should have in
in medicine they call a differential
diagnosis where they say I'm gonna order
this test and based on the results of
this you know whatever blood test I will
be able to rule out a bunch of stuff and
confirm some other things so every test
should have this kind of maybe this is
an information theory the thing should
be able to differentiate good programs
from bad programs if you have a test and
it doesn't do anything to advance your
understanding of good programs and bad
programs and that's probably a useless
test but if you took the space of all
possible programs to solve your problem
you know almost all of them won't and a
few of them will a test should should
should lop off a big portion of that
space and say nope all any program that
doesn't satisfy this test is definitely
not going to solve the real problem so
there's a part of that and then there's
a sense of redundancy if you have a
bunch of tests that tell you exactly the
same thing then I would look to see
which of them adds the least value and
delete them but they have to they have
to really cover exactly the same cases
do you think that all the other design
principles that we all know for general
programming also play for for the test
code like you all these like like dry
and whatever dry in particular I don't
subscribe to for test code because I
want my tests to read like a story so
one of the things the features in j-unit
is that you can if you have tests set up
in a superclass it will be run
before the test is run so you can you
know you can extract out some common set
up code between several different test
classes would you do that three or four
layers and now now the tests can be very
terse right the test just says you know
some object some message here's the
return value well but to understand
what's really going on there to
understand the story you I have to look
at the class and its setup and I have to
look at the superclass and its setup and
I have to look at its superclass and set
up by the time I'm done with that right
the you know it's it's like telling
someone the punchline to the joke
without telling telling them the whole
the whole setup you know it was the
priest you know it's not funny because
you don't you don't have the whole setup
now I hope I haven't defended any
priests who listen to the podcast but
can you observe or do you observe any
other really strange phenomena and
testing was a couple of really weird
ones so there's one that I that I can't
explain that's really useful and there's
one that's just weird
so the the useful one is that tests
don't fail at random if you take a
population of tests and you you run them
while doing normal development if a test
fails it's very it's much more likely to
fail soon thereafter so for most tests
once they start passing they'll never
again fail and this is based on looking
at hundreds of millions of test runs
representing like 50 person years worth
of development so once the test starts
working it's just going to keep working
if it ever fails then it's very likely
to fail a much more likely to fail the
next time you run it so we use that in
j-unit max which is this continuous
testing tool for for clips and Java to
prioritize tests so that you run the
tests that are most likely to fail first
so that while your attention is really
on the tests that you're running you get
most of the feedback because really if
you could prove and you I suppose you
could with a you know a coverage tester
and some static analysis you could prove
that this if this test succeeded last
time it'll succeed this time then you
don't even have to run it at all the
this recent failure phenomenon is a
heuristic that's a lot cheaper to to
calculate because you just have to have
a little bit of memory about what's
happened in the past and it lets you
also prioritize the test and say well
let me run these first since they're
seemingly fragile you know brand-new
test run first tests that have failed
recently run first so that that's a true
and useful phenomenon that I maybe
wouldn't have guessed at but makes sense
the other one is that the if you look at
any test suite the time it takes to run
the tests some tests are shorter and
some tests are longer the distribution
of that is a power-law so you'll have
lots and lots of tests that will run
very quickly and a few tests that'll
take a very long time to run if you
create a histogram plot it on a log-log
graph you get this really ridiculously
straight line so I don't I can't explain
why that's true but I've looked at I've
seen it in enough data sets to believe
that it's pretty much universal what you
in in such a case would you split that
into two different let's see sweets or
so saying run the long running tests
less frequently or only doing the
nightly builder so to keep the you
running the whole tests quick well I
think there's that that would be
certainly be one thing you could do and
you would what that power law
distribution says is that most of the
tests can be run
in a small fraction of the time because
the outliers are so big so that you
could split it up that way and indeed
when J and Max runs it runs the short
running tests first what I haven't
confirmed and I would love to have more
data on is whether long running tests
are more likely to fail all right kind
of the the worst the worst outcome would
be the longer a test takes to run the
more information than it generates and
and the best would be if if there's no
correlation so if you want confidence
that the code is running all you have to
do is run the the short running tests
and you get most of the confidence can
you tell us a little bit more about J
Union maxi and you mentioned it I think
some time now can tell us a little bit
more what is it exactly sure so it's a
it's a continuous tester for clips so if
you're in a project Java project in
Eclipse you out at the source code you
save it all the tests for the project or
run automatically and the the metaphor
is is just like the compiler so you make
a change to your source code the
compiler runs you get feedback right
away there's not a separate testing
there's not a separate compiler tool
there you go and execute in Eclipse and
with max there's not a separate testing
tool there's not a separate window you
go to you just get the feedback right
away so it came out of my frustration as
I ran tests the the more I did TDD the
more I ran the tests the more frequently
I ran the tests so take the J unit test
suite for example it takes about 10
seconds to execute if you're running
that 20 times an hour which is probably
a conservative estimate and you wait
till the end every time you run it you
know you can you can just do the math
and say you know depending on what my
billing rate is here's how much money
per hour I'm spending on on just waiting
for the tests to complete so I wanted to
cut that down
well this test prioritization trick and
the integration into the the tests
appear failed tests appear like compile
error so it's it shows up in the you
know right in your source code you don't
have to Swit switch context when you get
test results back so the combination of
that means that I only have to wait a
couple of seconds before I say yeah
that's good enough now I can get back to
coding well so you know you take the the
every time I do the numbers it seems
ridiculous so I'll leave that as an
exercise to your readers to figure out
how long they're spending waiting for
tests and how much money they could save
by having test results in in say 10
percent of that time it turns out to be
a substantial number so part of it part
of them my motivation was that
frustration with just I was spending
more of my time waiting for test results
than I wanted and part of my motivation
was I wanted a way to make a living
programming you know I can yeah I can
fly around give talks do consulting and
so on but you know I live in paradise so
I'd rather not do that and I love
programming so you know is there a way
that I can make my living programming so
it was a combination of the theoretical
work on tests and the behavior of real
test Suites in the wild my personal
motivation wanting to get more out of
programming and spend less time waiting
and this desire to to create a way of
supporting myself and my family and
college tuitions and paying for goat
feed and so on through a an activity
that I still love to engage in and so
that's Jana max cool and do I need to
write special tests for you or does it
run just my general J unit tests in
version 3 for whatever
yep yep so it's a one way to look at it
is it's a replacement for the the J unit
test runner that comes bundled with a
clip
okay so so no special code in my test
code for that no no not at all it just
gives you the results with less waiting
oh great
where can I get the JUnit max calm okay
dot-com does not sound like open source
it's some kind of you need need to pay
some amount for you yes so it's a
hundred dollars a year okay and every
time I do the math to figure it out it
pays for itself about every two days in
time safe great so we talked a lot about
testing and in the past testing in the
history let's now try to take a look
into the future what do you expect
well the the things that I see I think J
you know max is is kind of my take on
where the future is going that tests
will become as important to programming
as the as the compiler is when the tests
are giving you value every minute then
you're willing to invest quite a bit
more in in creating them I think there's
a big trend coming in design for
testability so a system like eclipse I
think is beautifully designed but it's
difficult to write tests that are
concise and run quickly for Eclipse
functionality there there's certainly
another way to design exactly that same
functionality for which it would be easy
to write unit tests that would execute
quickly and be isolated from from you
know extraneous failures and so on but
like exactly how do you do that
I think is there's a whole lot of
learning to be done there but as the
value of tests increases then the value
of learning about those design skills
goes up at the same time and I think
that there'll be a virtuous cycle of
more tests driving the need for more
testable designs which make the tests
less costly and more valuable which
leads to more tests
centers it so I think that's that's
something that I expect and then just
running tests more frequently more of
the tests running more of the time so
kind of the next stage for something
like max if you wanted to get more
feedback per clock second of the of the
cus of the programmers experience you'll
need to start executing tests in
parallel and in massive parallel any
other pearls of wisdom you would like to
share with our listeners the obvious
last question oh no I really I I have
grown okay so here's my pearl of wisdom
which is a be distrustful of pearls of
wisdom
III don't trust the simple morals that
people come up with at the end of their
stories I'm very happy to listen to the
stories but when then they when then
they conclude you know therefore you
should do things just like I did them I
think it misses a lot of context so so
listen to stories and tell stories there
that's my uh that's my moral which isn't
a story so you can just disregard it but
then I have to ask you another maybe
different difficult question what do you
think will suffer engineering look like
in five years the big the big trend is
towards more frequent deployment and
that drives everything else all the
social changes that need to happen all
the technical changes that need to
happen the the changes in practice in
language and infrastructure you know if
you're deploying fifty times a day you
know a database has to look different
your deployments tag has to look
different your the the current
separation of ops and dev just ask to go
away marketing sales business models
everything changes when you're deploying
very very frequently and that's a trend
that is gathering momentum and I don't
see any place where that's going to stop
great maybe we should we could spend
another episode talking about continuous
deployment I'd love to yeah great so for
this episode thank you very very very
much for your time that's my pleasure
thank you thank you very much credit RTC
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dot net if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at SC - radio net or if you're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas on top